Guide to the John Winthrop Platner Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John Winthrop Platner papers
1896-1921
RG 292
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(9 boxes)
The collection documents Platner's work as a professor at Harvard College and Andover Theological seminary.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1865 May 15 Born in Lee, MA
1885 Graduated from Yale College
1885-1890 Private tutor
1893 Graduated from Union Theological Seminary, New York
1893-1895 European Fellow, University of Berlin
1895-1896 Instructor in History of Religion and Apologetics, Union Theological Seminary
1896-1901 Assistant Professor of Ecclesiastical History, Harvard College
1901 Received A.M., Yale College
1901 June 18 Ordained (Congregational), First Congregational Church, Cambridge, MA
1901-1904 Taylor Professor of History, Andover Theological Seminary
1904-1921 Brown Professor of Ecclesiastical History, Andover Theological Seminary
1919-1921 Dean, Andover Theological Seminary
1921 March 18 Died, Cambridge, MA
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School, 2017
Scope and Contents
The John Winthrop Platner Papers, 1896-1921, document the professional work of Platner. Since most material is undated, dates of the collection are assigned to parallel his teaching at Harvard College and Andover Theological Seminary. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: poem, correspondence, addresses, lectures, unpublished manuscript titled "The history of early Christian literature," and miscellaneous notes and clippings. The bulk of the collection is class lectures.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series: Series I. Poem
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Addresses
Series IV. Lectures
Series V. Unpublished manuscript
Series VI. Notes and Clippings
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
- Poem, Series I
  - Lines written in Cambridge on the occasion of the death of Ex Gov. W. E. Russell, 1896 July 18 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Letters from William A. Knight, to/from C. C. Carpenter and Milton Newberry Franz (5 letters, 1 telegram), 1905–1917 (Box 1)
- Addresses, Series III
  - The war with Spain, no date (Box 1)
  - Albrecht Ritschl and the Study of Early Church History. Harvard Divinity School,opening address, 1896 October 2 (Box 1)
  - Papal Elections. Radcliffe History Club, 1899 December 11 (Box 1)
  - Progress in Theology. Winthrop Club, 1910 April 4 (Box 1)
- Lectures, Series IV
  - Not related to courses
    - Sunday Noon Lectures, Central Congregational Church, Boston, No date (Box 1)
    - Foreign Missions from the Protestant Churches of the United States during the Nineteenth Century. Hyde Lectures, Andover Theological Seminary, 1901–1902 (Box 1)
    - The Life and Times of Jesus Christ. The Twentieth Century Club, Boston (eight lectures on the life of Christ), 1905 (Box 1)
    - Great Leaders of the Early Church. Sunday Noon Lectures, Central Congregational Church, Boston. (ten lectures), 1906 (Box 1)
    - The History of Andover Theological Seminary, A Centennial Retrospect, Southworth Lectures, ATS (six lectures), 1908 (Box 1)
    - The Eastern Church. King's Chapel Lectures, Lowell Institute (three lectures), 1911 (Box 2)
    - The Homiletical Use of Church History, Andover Theological Seminary (four lectures), 1914 (Box 2)
  - Course lectures
    - Courses taught at Harvard College
      - The Elements of Christianity. History of Religions 10 (three folders) (Box 3)
      - The History of the Church Since the Reformation History 21 (ten folders) (Box 3)
      - The History of the Early Church (also taught at Radcliffe College) (29 folders) (Box 3)
      - History 20 (one folder) (Box 3)
    - Courses taught at Harvard Divinity School
      - The Apostolic Fathers (two folders) (Box 3)
      - Bible Class on the Old Testament (four folders) (Box 4)
      - History 1 (four folders) (Box 4)
    - Courses taught at Andover Theological Seminary
      - Christian Institutions (19 folders) (Box 5)
      - Church History in Outline (17 folders) (Box 5)
      - History of Christian Doctrine (18 folders) (Box 6)
      - History of Modern Theology (five folders) (Box 7)
      - History of the New Testament Canon (five folders) (Box 7)
      - Modern Foreign Missions (six folders) (Box 8)
  - Material related to courses
    - Lists of readings
      - Andover Theological Seminary: Christian Institutions; History of the Church in England (Box 8)
    - Examinations
      - Harvard College: The Elements of Christianity (Box 8)
      - Andover Theological Seminary: Christian Institutions; Church History in Outline; History of Christian Doctrine; History of Early Christian Literature; History of the Canon and Text of the New Testament; History of the Church in England; Modern Foreign Mission (Box 8)
    - Lists of students and grades
      - Harvard College: Elements of Christianity; History 21 (Box 8)
      - Radcliffe College (Box 8)
      - Andover Theological Seminary: Christian Institutions; Church History in Outline; The History of Early Christian Literature History of Christian Doctrine; The History of the Church in England;; Modern Foreign Missions (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous material related to courses
      - Andover Theological Seminary: History of the Church in England (Box 8)
- Unpublished Manuscript, Series V
  - The History of Early Christian Literature. Ten chapters, with an introduction, and an outline of chapters 11-14 (19 folders). (Box 9)
    Scope and Contents
    Appears to be a modification of his lecture notes for the course, The History of Early Christian Literature, taught at ATS.
- Notes and Clippings, Series VI
  - fragments (two folders) (Box 9)
  - Aristides and Justin Martyr (four folders) (Box 9)
  - Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History (five folders) (Box 9)
  - Jerome--Seminary Notes 1900-1901 (two folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Education (one folder) (Box 9)
  - Notes on Italy--Places, History, Art, etc. (one folder) (Box 9)
  - Papal Elections (two folders) (Box 9)
  - Pamphlets and clippings: mostly dealing with the Rockefeller gift of $100,000 to the ABCFM in 1905, and the ensuing controversy (Box 9)